When a week ago today, Mr. Speaker, I asked the House to fix this afternoon as the occasion
for a statement, I feared it would be my hard lot to announce the greatest military disaster
in our long history. I thought, and some good judges agreed with me, that perhaps 20,000
or 30,000 men might be re-embarked. But it certainly seemed that the whole of the French
First Army and the whole of the British Expeditionary Force north of the Amiens-Abbeville gap would
be broken up in the open field, or else would have to capitulate for lack of food and ammunition.
These were the hard and heavy tidings for which I called upon the House and the nation
to prepare themselves a week ago. The whole root and core and brain of the British Army,
on which and around which we were to build and are to build, the great British armies
in the later years of the war seemed about to perish upon the field or be led into an
ignominious and starving captivity. The enemy attacked us on all sides with great strength
and fierceness. And their main power, the power of their far more numerous air force,
was thrown into the battle or else concentrated upon Dunkirk and the beaches. Pressing in upon
the narrow exit, both from the east and from the west, the enemy began to fire with cannon
upon the beaches by which alone the shipping could approach or depart. They sowed magnetic
mines in the channels and seas. They sent repeated waves of hostile aircraft, sometimes more than a
hundred strong in one formation, to cast their bombs upon the single pier that remained
and upon the sand dunes on which the troops had their only shelter. Their U-boats, one
of which was sunk, and their motor launchers took the toll of the vast traffic which now
began. For four or five days an intense struggle reigned. All their armoured divisions, or
what was left of them, together with great masses of infantry and artillery, hurled themselves
in vain upon the ever-narrowing, ever-contracting appendix within which the British and French
armies fought. Meanwhile the Royal Navy, with the willing help of countless merchant seamen,
strained every nerve to embark the British and Allied troops. Two hundred and twenty
light warships and six hundred and fifty other vessels were engaged. They had to operate
upon the difficult coast, and often in adverse weather, under an almost ceaseless hail of
bombs and an increasing concentration of artillery fire. Nor were the seas, as I have said, themselves
free from mines and torpedoes. It was in conditions such as these that our men carried
on with little or no rest, for days and nights on end, making trip after trip across the
dangerous waters, bringing with them, always, men whom they had rescued. The numbers they
have brought back are the measure of their devotion and their courage. The hospital ships
which brought off many thousands of British and French wounded, being so plainly marked,
were a special target for Nazi bombs, but the men and women on board them never faltered
in their duty. Meanwhile, the Royal Air Force, which had already been intervening in the
battle, so far as its range would allow, from our home bases, now used part of its
main metropolitan fighter strength and struck at the German bombers and at the fighters,
which in large numbers protected them. This struggle was protracted and fierce. Suddenly
the scene had cleared. The crash and thunder, as for the moment, but only for the moment,
died away. A miracle of deliverance, achieved by valour, by perseverance, by perfect discipline,
by faultless service, by resource, by skill, by unconquerable fidelity, is manifest to
us all. The enemy was hurled back by the retreating British troops. They were so roughly
handled that he did not carry their departure seriously. Sir, we must be very careful not to
assign to this deliverance the attributes of a victory. Wars are not won by evacuations,
but there was a victory inside this deliverance, which should be noted. It was gained by the Air
Force. Many of our soldiers coming back have not seen the Air Force at work. They saw only the
bombers, which escaped its protective attack. They underrated its achievements. I've heard
much talk of this, and that is why I go out of my way to say this. I will tell you about it.
This was a great trial of strength between the British and German air forces. Can you conceive
a greater objective for the Germans in the air than to make evacuation from these beaches
impossible, and to sink all these ships, which were displayed almost to the extent of thousands?
Could there have been an objective of greater military importance and significance for the
whole purpose of the wars of this? They tried hard, and they were beaten back. They were frustrated in
their task. We got the army away, and they have paid fourfold for any losses which they have
inflicted. Sir, when we consider how much greater would be our advantage in defending the air above
this island against an overseas attack, I must say that I find in these facts a sure basis upon
which practical and reassuring thoughts may rest. I will pay my tribute to these young airmen. The
great French army was very largely, for the time being, cast back and disturbed by the onrush of
a few thousands of armored vehicles. May it not also be that the cause of civilization itself
will be defended by the skill and devotion of a few thousand airmen. There never has been, I suppose,
in all the world, in all the history of war, such an opportunity for use. The Knights of the Round
Table, the Crusaders, all fall back into the past, not only distant, but prosaic. These young men
going forth every morn to guard their native land and all that we stand for, holding in their hands
these instruments of colossal and shattering power, of whom it may be said that every morn brought
forth a noble chance, and every chance brought forth a noble knight, deserve our gratitude. Yes,
all the brave men, in so many ways and on so many occasions, are ready and continue ready to give
life and all for their native land. Nevertheless, our thankfulness at the escape of our army and so
many men whose loved ones have passed through an agonizing week does not blind us to the fact that
what happened in France and Belgium, it's a colossal military disaster. The French army has
been weakened, the Belgian army has been lost, a large part of those fortified lines upon which
so much faith has been reposed, is gone. Many valuable mining districts and factories have
passed into the enemy's possession, the whole of the Channel ports are in its hands, with all the
tragic consequences that follow from that, and we must expect another blow to be struck almost
immediately at us or at France. We are told, sir, that Herr Hitler has a plan for invading the British
Isles. This has often been thought of before. When Napoleon laid boulogne for a year with his
flat-bottomed boats and his grand army, he was told by someone, there are bitter weeds in England.
There are certainly a great many more of them since the British expeditionary force returned.
Sir, I have myself full confidence that if all do their duty, if nothing is neglected, and if the
best arrangements are made, as they are being made, we shall prove ourselves once more able to defend
our island home, to ride out the storm of war, and to outlive the menace of tyranny, if necessary,
for years, if necessary, alone. At any rate, that is what we are going to try to do. That is the
resolve of His Majesty's government, every man of them. That is the will of Parliament and the nation.
The British Empire and the French Republic, linked together in their cause and in their need, will
defend to the death their native soil, aiding each other like good comrades to the utmost of their
strength. We shall go on to the end. We shall fight in France. We shall fight on the seas and oceans.
We shall fight with growing confidence and growing strength in the air. We shall defend our island,
whatever the cost may be. We shall fight on the beaches. We shall fight on the landing grounds.
We shall fight in the fields and in the streets. We shall fight in the hills. We shall never surrender.
And if, which I do not for a moment believe, this island or a large part of it were subjugated and
starving, then our empire, beyond the seas, armed and guarded by the British fleet, would carry on
the struggle until, in God's good time, the new world, with all its power and might, steps forth to the
rescue and the liberation of the old.